In the last lecture we finished the set up of our project,
Son dersimizde, projelerimizi tamamladk.
now I want to start developing the app. For that, I'll
imdi bunun iin uygulama gelitirmeye balamak istiyorum.
first of all run npm start to start this development server so that we can see the app run on localhost:
ncelikle Ron NPM, bu gelitirme sunucusunu balatmaya balar, bylece uygulamann localhost 3000
3000.
zerinde almasn grebiliriz.
Make sure you're saving all files so that you don't get the compilation errors I got
Elindeki derleme oklarn almamak iin tm dosyalar kaydettiinizden emin olun.
and with that you will basically not see anything because we emptied the app.js file,
Ayrca sa'nn dt uygulama noktasn boalttmz iin temelde hibir ey gremiyorsunuz.
it's just having an empty div,
Sadece bo bir div var.
obviously we don't see content.
Belli ki ierik grmyoruz.
Now let's start implementing the components we sketched out in the previous lectures and there are actually
imdi, nceki derslerde tasvir ettiimiz bileenleri uygulamaya balayalm ve
a couple of components we need but we can kind of separate our project into two branches,
aslnda ihtiyacmz olan birka bileen var, ancak projemizi iki eye ayralm.
well overall these branches, we got a layout component but below that we basically have navigation related
Tamamen bu projeler bir bileeni ortaya koyduk ancak aada temel olarak ara ubuu
components like the toolbar and the sideDrawer and we have to meat of our application, the burger builder.
ve yan ekmece gibi gezinme ile ilgili bileenlere sahibiz ve burger oluturucumuza bavurmamz gerekiyor.
Now I'd say let's start with the burger builder then, that's probably the more fun part to start with.
imdi burger Boler'le balayalm, bu muhtemelen balamak iin daha elenceli bir blm.
Now for that, I first of all will create that layout component though which will kind of be a wrapper
imdi her eyden nce, hangi tr bir ara ubuu ve burger uygulayarak bir sarc
implementing the toolbar and the burger
olacak ekilde dzen bileen tedavi edeceiz.
builder then and later in this course, once we add routing and more pages to our application,
Daha sonra, uygulamanza ynlendirme ve daha fazla sayfa ekledikten sonra bu derste daha da katlyorum.
we will take advantage of this layout where the toolbar will always be there but where we will then
Ara ubuunun her zaman orada olaca bu dzenin avantajndan yararlanacaz,
switch the page which is rendered in the content area of the layout so to say. Now we could simply turn
ancak burada, mizanpajn ierik alannda oluturulmu sayfay deitireceiz, bylece imdi, uygulamay bir
the app.js file into a layout because it basically is the root component of our application and that
yerletirmeye dntrecek ekilde dndrebileceimizi syledik temelde uygulamanzn kk bileenidir ve mkemmel
would be a perfectly fine approach,
bir yaklam olacaktr.
I will still create a separate component for that though, to have a component entirely focusing on the
Bunun iin yine de ayr bir bileeni ele alacam, ancak dzen zerinde tamamen duran bir
layout.
bileene sahip olmalym.
Now for that, I'll creaate a new subfolder in the source folder and I will name it components.
imdi kaynak klasr ultra kullanm alt klasr ve bileenleri adn vereceim.
I will create a second subfolder which I'll name containers,
Kaplar adlandran ikinci bir alt klasr oluturacam.
now keep in mind, containers are basically stateful components, so typically components created with the
imdi, konteynrlar esas olarak durum bilgisi olan bileenler olduundan, bileenler klasre
class keyword whereas components, going into the components folder, are stateless components,
giren bileenler devlet son bileenleri iken bileenlerin snf anahtar kelime ile oluturulduunu aklnzda tutun.
typically functional components.
Tipik olarak ilevsel bileenler.
Now I will create a layout in the components folder because right now, I don't need to manage any states
imdi komponentler klasrne yerletirmeye alacam, nk u anda herhangi bir eyaleti orada ynetmek zorunda
there.
deilim.
So in components, I'll create a subfolder which I'll name Layout with a capital L and in layout, I will
Bylece bileenlerin hepsinde bir L dizilinceye kadar adlandrlacak bir alt klasr oluturulur
create a layout.js file so that we have this layout component placed in that folder.
ve mizanpajda J mizanpajn dosya olarak oluturur, bylece bu mizanpaj bileeni bu klasre yerletirilir.
That is a typical project setup you use in react, having a components and a containers folder. Other
grdmz klasrler zerinde bir bileenleri ve bir kapsayclar klasr kullanp yeniden davranmay ayarlar.
folders you often see are assets folder,
Bu, tipik bir proje olup, elerinizi genellikle
we will use this later once we add a logo
Bunu, daha sonra logoyu eklediimizde kullanacaz.
and you might also have a folder for the redux store and so on,
Ayrca bir klasre sahip olabilirsiniz veya X maazasn vb. Okumak iin ileri alabilirsiniz.
we haven't even learned about that.
Bunu daha nce rendik bile deil.
We will add it once we got that.
Onu bulduktan sonra ekleyeceiz.
So back to the layout then, there I will create a normal functional component and store it in a constant
Peki dzene dndmde orada normal bir ilevsel bileen oluturacam ve sabit olarak adlandrlm bir
named layout
adreste saklayacam.
and there is my function
Ve iim orada.
and now, let's have a look at how this function should look like or how the jsx exported by that
Ve imdi bu ilevin nasl grnmesi gerektiine veya bu ilev tarafndan ihra edilen Julias X'in
function should look like. There
Dare'e nasl grnmesi gerektiine bir gz atalm.
I basically want to have two areas you could say, I'll have a div,
Temelde iki alann hepsinin farkl olduunu sylemek isterim.
for now, just a placeholder which will hold my toolbar, my sideDrawer and probably for the sideDrawer,
imdilik, ara ubuumu yan ekmecemde ve muhtemelen yan ekmece iin veya bir zemin olarak tutacak
also a backdrop.
bir yer tutucusu.
So we will need to replace this div with three components later on,
Dolaysyla, bu div'  bileenle daha sonra deitirmeniz gerekecek.
we also did plan this in the previous lectures. Below this part, we'll have a main area
Bunu bir nceki blmde de yaptmz bu blm ana alana sahip olacak.
and this is the normal main element provided by html and there I want to output the component we wrap
H M L tarafndan salanan normal ana unsur ve bu dzende saracamz bileeni kt olarak istiyorum.
with this layout.
Ve bu,
So I will use props.children and for that of course, I need to import props or not import it, excuse
Bu yzden pervane ocuklarm kullanacam ve bunun iin de ithal etmek gerekiyor pervane ithal
me, get it as argument.
edilmiyor Afedersiniz, argman olarak alrsnz.
Now this allows us to simply use this layout component as a wrapper around the core content component
imdi, bu, bu dzen bileenini, ekirdek ierik bileeni etrafnda bir sarmalayc olarak kullanmamza olanak tanr;
we want to render to the screen.
bylece, ekranda grntlenmek istiyoruz.
Now here we get an error in the IDE because one important thing is missing, the import of the react package
imdi burada kimlii hatal buluyoruz, nk nemli bir ey tepki paketinin ie aktarlmad ya da yeniden
or the react object I should say from on the react package.
hareket paketinde sylemem gereken nesneye tepki veriyor musunuz.
Once we added this, we still see an error because we have adjacent jsx elements.
Bir keresinde bunlar bulduk, hatay gryoruz, nk komu Julias X elerine sahibiz.
Now I taught you that there are basically two solutions to that,
imdi sana bunun temelde iki zm olduunu rettim.
do you remember them?
Onlar hatrlyor musun.
Well for one, we could return an array here instead of jsx which is sitting next to each other.
Birincisi, birbirine bitiik olan X yerine J dizisi dndrebiliriz.
If we return an array and give each item a key, we are allowed to kind of return adjacent elements.
Her bir eye bir anahtar getirip puan verdiysek, komu elere geri dn yapmalarna izin verilir.
The alternative is to create such an auxiliary higher order component which I showed you in the last
Alternatif, son ders modlnde size gsterdiim bu tr yardmc maddeyi yksek dereceli
course module,
bir bileen oluturmaktr.
it serves only one purpose,
Tek bir amaca hizmet eder.
wrapping something and immediately outputting it
Bir ey sarmak ve hemen kt vermek.
but hence fulfilling the requirement of having a wrapping component.
Fakat sarmal bir bileene sahip olma gereksinimini hl dolduruyor.
I will use this,
Bunu kullanacam.
we also have of course the third option of wrapping everything in a div here or another element but
Elbette her eyi bir fark yl veya baka bir e iinde sarmalamay erteleme seeneine sahibiz, ancak l
I don't need that div or any array element,
div veya herhangi bir dizi esine ihtiyacm yok.
actually I want to have adjacent elements.
Aslnda bitiik elemanlara sahip olmak istiyorum.
That is why I will go with the higher order component approach and create search utility auxiliary component.
Bu yzden yksek sipari bileeni yaklamyla gideceim ve bunun iin arama yardmc yardmc bileen
For that,
oluturacam.
I'll create a new folder in the source folder
Kaynak klasrnde yeni bir klasr oluturacam.
hoc for higher order component and there, I will create an aux.js file.
Agios yksek mertebeden bileenler gryor ve Oxcart Julias dosyasn deneyeceim.
Now the auxiliary component is really really simple,
imdi d bileen gerekten ok basit.
it's a functional component, a stateless component therefore,
Bu nedenle, ilevsel bir bileen durumu daha az bileen.
I will name it aux
Ve ona adlarn syleyeceim.
and here I just get props as an input and I returned props.children, nothing else,
Ve burada sadece bir sahne alm olarak girdim ve pervane ocuklarna baka bir ey getirmedim.
no wrapping element,
Sarg eleman yok.
we don't even have any jsx in this file which is also why we don't have to import react from react.
Bu dosyada herhangi bir js Xon bile yok nk bu da tepki vermeden yeniden eylem almak zorunda deiliz.
I will then export aux as the default in this file and save the file
Ardndan, bu dosyalar varsaylan olarak alks olarak da aktaracam ve dosyay kaydedeceim.
and now back in the layout file, I can import Aux with a capital A like for all custom components you
imdi tekrar dzen dosyasnda, kullanmak istediiniz tm zel bileenler gibi, sermayesi A
want to use from
olan alks'leri ie aktarabilirim.
and now we have to move up until we are at the source folder level and there from the hoc folder from
Ve imdi, kaynak klasr seviyesine gelinceye ve oradan da kz dosyasndaki HLC klasr gelene
the aux file
kadar yukar kmalyz.
without .js at the end because keep in mind, our build workflow will add this file extension for
Sonunda nokta JSA olmadan, i akmzn javascript dosyalar iin otomatik olarak bu dosya
javascript files automatically. And now I can wrap everything here with this auxiliary component so
uzantsn ekleyeceini aklnzda bulundurun ve imdi burada her eyi bu yardmc bileenle saralm nk
that we now fulfill the requirement of having a wrapping root element.
artk bir kaydrma kk esine sahip olma gereksinimini yerine getiriyoruz.
Finally let me export this layout function as the default for this file
Sonunda bu dosyann varsaylan olarak bu dzen ilevini da aktarmama izin verin.
and now with that, we can use it in the app.js file
Ve imdi bununla uygulamada aadaki gibi kullanabilirsiniz.
in our root component.
Kk bileenimizde.
Now granted, you could also go to the index file, import layout here and simply render the layout function
imdi, burada dizin dosyas alma ilevine gidebilir ve basite yerleim ilevini kk bileen
as the root component.
olarak oluturabilirsiniz.
That's basically the same solution as making the app.js file
Temelde, bunu aadaki gibi yapmakla ayn zm.
the root component.
Kk bileen.
You could absolutely do that and that wouldn't be wrong,
Kesinlikle yapabilirdiniz ve bu yanl olmayacaktr.
it's just my personal decision to have this root component in case I should ever decide to restructure
farkl dzenler oluturulabilir veya bu gibi uygulama iin olduu gibi bir ey yapabilir.
the app, add some state to my root component, maybe conditionally render different layouts or do anything
Bu kk bileenine sahip olmak benim kiisel kararm; bu yzden, uygulamann bir aamada kk bileenime yeniden
like that. For the app as it is,
yaplandrmaya karar vermem gerektiinde, artl olarak
we could definitely turn the app component itself into the layout.
Uygulama bileeninin kendisini dzen iine evirebiliriz.
Now enough talk about that,
imdi yeterince konualm.
let's import our Layout component then with a capital L from
Layout bileenini sonra L ba harfli ithal edelim.
and now we have to go into the components folder into the layout folder and there to the layout.js
Ve imdi, bileen klasrne dzen klasrne gitmeliyiz ve dzen olmas iin var.
file, and now we can simply render layout and this should now not be a self-closing component because
JS dosyas ve imdi sadece dzeni ileyebiliriz ve bu artk bir kapan bileeni
the idea behind the whole layout is that I can wrap another component with it.
olmamal nk tm dzenin ardndaki fikir, bileeni kaydrp numaralandrmamzdr.
For now, let's simply wrap a paragraph just to see if this is working,
imdilik, sadece bir paragrafn sadece alp almadn grmek iin sarmalayalm.
if we are correctly passing this to layout but later we will of course wrap a real component,
Bunu dzgn bir ekilde aktarmak iin harcarsak ancak daha sonra gerek bir bileeni saralm.
the page we actually want to display with it.
Aslnda bununla oynamak istediimiz sayfa.
So make sure all files are saved and then head over to your localhost:3000 page,
Bu nedenle tm dosyalarn kaydedildiinden emin olun ve daha sonra yerel ana bilgisayar 3000 sayfanza ynelin.
make sure your development server is running and there you should see our placeholder for the toolbar,
Gelitirme sunucunuzun altndan emin olun ve oradaki ara ubuu iin yer tutucumuzun ieriden ieri girmesini
for the sideDrawer, for the backdrop and so on
veya bir arka plan ekleyeceinizi grmeniz gerekir.
and you also see the test paragraph I just added.
Ayrca eklediim test paragrafn da gryorsunuz.
If you inspect everything, you will notice that we don't use our open sans font though because we haven't
fark yaz tipini kullanmadmz farkedeceksiniz, nk eklemedik nk bunu da dzeltin.
added it, so let's fix this too,
Hereyi beklerseniz, ak
let's go to index.css,
Bir dahaki sefere gidelim.
we did add the import to the public folder,
Ortak klasre ie aktarrken yaptmz gibi bizi grn.
so here we simply have to add open sans like this, as our main font
Dolaysyla burada, byle bir mantkl ana fonumuz olarak eklemeliyiz.
and use sans-serif as a backup font and now you see the font changed
Ve sen Sarath' yedekleme fonu olarak gnderiyorsun ve imdi telefonun deitiini gryorsun.
and in the elements tab,
Ve ardndan eler sekmesi.
you'll also see that now it is applied.
Ayrca uygulandn da gryorsunuz.
With that, we got the root of our application finished for now,
Bununla birlikte, bavurumuzun atsn imdilik bitirdik.
there is of course a lot of work left regarding the navigation here, toolbar and everything
Elbette, gezinme ubuu ve her eyle ilgili ok fazla alma kald.
but since we don't have multiple pages right now, we don't need to take care about the navigation right
Ancak u anda birden fazla sayfamz olmadndan u anda navigasyona zen gstermemiz
now.
gerekmiyor.
So let's instead focus on the core functionality of our application,
Bunun yerine, uygulamanzn temel ilevlerine odaklanalm.
the burger builder. We'll start implementing that in the next lectures.
Burger kurucusu bunu bir sonraki derslerde uygulamaya balayacak.